Guide to the John Hill Print Collection [1799]-1836 PR 217
New-York Historical Society
John Hill Print Collection
[1799]-1836
New-York Historical Society
PR 217
0.63 Linear feet (111 Prints)
Collection of aquatints by John Hill, mainly of New York City and the Hudson Valley.
Provenance
All the early English engravings were given on March 1, 1957 by Leroy E. Kimball. Other prints came from a variety of donors.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. See guidelines in Print Room for details.
Biographical Note
John Hill was born in London in 1770, and was apprenticed as a youth to an engraver in that city. He became interested in the process of aquatinting, a technique wherein a metal plate is etched several times in order to create tonal gradations, resulting in a print that is easier to hand-color due to the variety of subtle tones produced. Hill began working in London under his own name in 1798, and mainly produced aquatints that were used for book illustrations.
In 1816, in order to support his family of six children, John Hill immigrated to Philadelphia, then a major center of publishing in the United States. His earliest American engravings were mainly city views, which were, as in England, published as book or magazine illustrations. He was able to earn enough in America to bring his family to join him in 1819. Most members of Hill's family, including his wife and daughters, worked alongside him in some capacity, helping pull proofs or hand-color prints. Hill's son, John William Hill (1812-1879) became a skilled painter as well as an engraver and assistant to his father.
Aquatint was little known in the United States in 1816 and Hill quickly became the pre-eminent artist in the medium. In 1819 he began his first major commission, engraving plates after paintings of American urban and rural views by Joshua Shaw. Twenty plates of these Picturesque Views of American Scenery were published in four separate issues from 1820 to 1821. Most of these plates were hand-colored by Hill and his family. Picturesque Views of American Scenery is considered to be the first major plate book published in the United States.
Shortly after the completion of Shaw's views, Hill was commissioned by New York printer Henry J. Megarey to engrave and color views of New York after the painter William G. Wall. The resulting Hudson River Portfolio (1821-1825) contained twenty views of New York State towns, cities, and landscapes. In 1822 Hill moved to New York City in order to work more intently on the Portfolio.
While in New York, Hill engraved several city views, including one of City Hall. The practice of aquatint flourished in the 1820s and 1830s, as did Hill's reputation and business. He issued many single engravings, including sporting prints, and illustrated his own drawing book, as well as several other books. Between 1830 and 1832, Hill engraved a series of five Erie Canal views after paintings by his teenage son John William Hill. Few of these views were ever finished as completed prints.
In 1837, Hill and his wife moved to Rockland County, New York, where they had purchased land near West Nyack. Hill died in 1850.
Source:
Koke, Richard J. "John Hill, Master of Aquatint" in The New-York Historical Society Quarterly, Vol. XLIII No. 1, January 1959, pp. 51-118.
Scope and Content Note
The John Hill Print Collection spans the period from ca. 1799 to 1836 and contains 111 early nineteenth century aquatints, including some of the first aquatints done in the United States. The collection is arranged into two series based on Hill's country of residence: English Work; and American Work.
Arrangement
Prints are arranged into two series and thereunder are filed by date.
Missing Title
Series I. English Work
Series II. American Work
Related Material at the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections
The Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Materials also holds two bound copies of Picturesque Views of American Scenery 1820 and one bound Hudson River Portfolio. A copy of Lucas' Progressive Drawing Book, with engravings by Hill, is in the N-YHS Library. Several of Hill's early American engravings appeared in William Meade's An experimental enquiry into the chemical properties and medicinal qualities of the principal mineral waters of Ballston and Saratoga, in the state of New-York, and in June to September 1817 issues of the Analectic Magazine, both of which are also held by the Library. Hill's account book from the years ca. 1820-1834 is in the N-YHS Manuscript Department (BV Hill, John). Several of Hill's drawings are held in the N-YHS Museum.
Proofs before letters; Illustrations.; Landscapes (representations); Aquatints (prints); Erie Canal (N.Y.) -- Pictorial works.; West Point (N.Y.) -- Pictorial works.; Niagara Falls (N.Y. and Ont.) -- Pictorial works.; New York (N.Y.) -- Pictorial works.; Hill, J. W. (John William), 1812-1879; Hill, John, 1770-1850; Lucas, Fielding, Jr., 1781-1854 -- Lucas' progressive drawing book; Shaw, Joshua, 1776-1860 -- Picturesque views of American scenery; United States Military Academy -- Pictorial works; Wall, William Guy, 1792-approximately 1864 -- Hudson River portfolio
- Series I: English Work
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I. English Work is made up of nine engravings Hill completed in England between ca. 1799 and 1812. Hill completed the aquatinting process on these prints, and probably some of the coloring, but did not line engrave them. Most of the prints in this series are colored bookplates. "Troops" is a plate from W. H. Pyne's Microcosm(1803-08), one of Hill's most important London engraving commissions. All but one are views of military costumes, engagements, or personnel.
  - "Swansey," after Thomas Rowlandson (1756-1827), published in Henry Wigstead's Remarks on a Tour to North and South Wales, in the Year 1797 (London: W. Wigstead, 1799) (Folder 1)
  - "Troops," after William Henry Pyne (1769-1843), published in William Henry Pyne's Microcosm (London: Pyne, 1803-1808)., 1802 (Folder 1)
  - "Field Day," after John Augustus Atkinson (1775-1831), published by William Miller, 1808 (Folder 1)
  - "Halt of Troops," after John Augustus Atkinson (1775-1831), published by William Miller, 1808 (Folder 1)
  - "Recruits," after John Augustus Atkinson (1775-1831), published by William Miller, [1808] (Folder 1)
  - "Sepoys," after John Augustus Atkinson (1775-1831), published by William Miller, 1808 (Folder 1)
  - "Settling Booth," after John Augustus Atkinson (1775-1831), published by William Miller, 1808 (Folder 1)
  - "Artillery, Warlike Machines and Soldiers of the 15th Century," colored aquatint after John Augustus Atkinson (1775-ca. 1833), from A Picturesque Representation of the Naval, Military and Miscellaneous Costumes of Great Britain (Colnaghi & Co., London, 1812.), 1811-1812 (Folder 1)
  - "Military costumes of the reign of King Henry VI, 1447," colored aquatint after John Augustus Atkinson (1775-ca. 1833), from A Picturesque Representation of the Naval, Military and Miscellaneous Costumes of Great Britain (Colnaghi & Co., London, 1812.) (Folder 1)
- Series II: American Work
  Series II. American Work includes 102 prints, representing fifty-five of Hill's engravings from the time after he moved to Philadelphia in 1816. In 1961, Richard J. Koke compiled A Checklist of American Engravings of John Hill, a chronological list of 161 prints made by Hill between 1816 and 1838. In the inventory that follows, the numbers Koke assigned to each of Hill's prints have been noted in brackets.
  This series includes one complete set of twenty colored plates from Picturesque Views of American Scenery and other colored and uncolored copies of many of the plates. Wrappers from the first three issues are included in the collection, as are the text pages that accompanied plates 3 through 20. In addition, there are three plates from a reissue of the book in 1835 by Thomas T. Ash, a Philadelphia printer.
  Ten of the twenty plates of the Hudson River Portfolio (1821-25) are represented here, as are engravings from Fielding Lucas' Lucas' Progressive Drawing Book (1827-28) and Hill's own Drawing Book of Landscape Scenery (1821). Other prints include views of New York City, Niagara Falls (after paintings by William James Bennett) and the United States Military Academy at West Point.
  An original print of "Fairmount Waterworks" is not present in the collection. However, after the aquistion of the original plate, The New-York Historical Society pulled two restrikes from that plate in 1960. The first of these was pulled from the uncleaned plate. After the plate was cleaned, a second print was made, but the engraved tones in the sky were lost.
  Several prints, mostly proofs before letters, are after John William Hill's five Erie Canal watercolors. These include three stages of "Unidentified Town and Canal Lock;"a stage two trial proof after the plate was etched in line, with the addition of figures and objects in the foreground; a stage three trial proof with a watercolor wash as guide for the aquatint tones; and a stage four print taken from the copperplate after the tonal aquating ground had been bitten into the plate.
  "Broadway, New York," the last print in this collection, was drawn and etched in line by Thomas Hornor. It is one of only a few American plates on which John Hill did only the tonal aquatinting.
  Hill line engraved, aquatinted and often colored the following prints. All prints are uncolored and first state unless otherwise noted.
  - unspecified
    - "The Conflagration of the Masonic Hall, Chestnut Street, Philadelphia," after Samuel Jones and John Lewis Krimmell (1789-1821), published sometime after 1819 (probably between 1862-1891) by William Smith, Philadelphia. (Folder 2)
      General note
      Second state. [Koke 25]
  - Aquatints after Joshua Shaw (1776-1860) from Picturesque Views of American Scenery 1820 (Philadelphia: M. Carey & Son, [1820-21]).
    - "Title Page, Vignette", 1819-1821 (Folder 3)
      Two copies, second state, one colored. [Koke 37]
    - "Washington's Sepulchre, Mount Vernon", 1819-1821 (Folder 4)
      Three copies, one colored. [Koke 38]
    - "View Above the Falls of Schuylkill", 1819-1821 (Folder 5)
      Two copies, one colored. [Koke 39]
    - "Jones Falls near Baltimore", 1819-1821 (Folder 6)
      Three copies, two colored. [Koke 40]
    - "View Near the Falls of Schuylkill", 1819-1821 (Folder 7)
      Three copies, one colored. [Koke 41]
    - "View of the Spot Where Gen. Ross Fell Near Baltimore", 1819-1821 (Folder 8)
      Four copies, two colored. [Koke 42]
    - "Falls of St. Anthony on the Mississippi", 1819-1821 (Folder 9)
      Three copies, two colored. [Koke 43]
    - "Lynnhaven Bay", 1819-1821 (Folder 10)
      Three copies, one colored. [Koke 44]
    - "Spirit Creek; near Augusta, Georgia", 1819-1821 (Folder 11)
      Four copies, one colored. [Koke 45]
    - "View by Moonlight, near Fayetteville", 1819-1821 (Folder 12)
      Three copies, two colored. [Koke 46]
    - "Burning of Savannah", 1819-1821 (Folder 13)
      Two copies, both colored [Koke 47]
    - "Norfolk; from Gosport, Virginia", 1819-1821 (Folder 14)
      Three copies, one colored. [Koke 48]
    - "View on the Wisahiccon, Pennsylvania", 1819-1821 (Folder 15)
      Colored. [Koke 49]
    - "Monument near North Point", 1819-1821 (Folder 16)
      Three copies, two colored. [Koke 50]
    - "Passaic Falls, New Jersey", 1819-1821 (Folder 17)
      Colored. [Koke 51]
    - "View on the North River", 1819-1821 (Folder 18)
      Three copies, all colored. [Koke 52]
    - "Hell Gate", 1819-1821 (Folder 19)
      Two copies, both colored. [Koke 53]
    - "Bolling's Dam, Petersburgh, Virginia", 1819-1821 (Folder 20)
      Four copies, two colored. [Koke 54]
    - "Oyster Cove", 1819-1821 (Folder 21)
      Two copies, one colored. [Koke 55]
    - "Passaic River Below the Falls", 1819-1821 (Folder 22)
      Colored. [Koke 56]
    - Paper covers from the first three issues, 1819-1821 (Folder 23)
    - Text plates 3-20 from the first three issues, 1819-1821 (Folder 24)
  - Aquatints after Joshua Shaw (1776-1860) from Picturesque Views of American Scenery 1820 (reissued Philadelphia: Thomas T. Ash, 1835).
    - "Lynnhaven Bay" (Folder 25)
      Second state. [Koke 44]
    - "View on the Wisahiccon, Pennsylvania" (Folder 25)
      Second state. [Koke 49]
    - "Monument near North Point" (Folder 25)
      Second state. [Koke 50]
    - "Passaic River Below the Falls" (Folder 25)
      Second state, colored. [Koke 56]
  - Colored aquatints from Drawing Book of Landscape Scenery. Studies from Nature. Executed by I. Hill 1821 (New York: Henry J. Megarey, 1821).
    - "Churches", 1821 (Folder 26)
      [Koke 65]
    - "Abbeys", 1821 (Folder 26)
      [Koke 68]
    - "Ruins", 1821 (Folder 26)
      [Koke 72]
  - Colored aquatints after William Guy Wall (1792-after 1864) from Wall's Hudson River Portfolio (New York: H.I. Megarey & W. B. Gilley, 1821-1825)
    - "The Junction of the Sacandaga and Hudson Rivers", 1821-1822 (Folder 27)
      Plate 2 [Koke 76]
    - "Hadley's Falls", 1821-1822 (Folder 27)
      Plate 5 [Koke 78]
    - "View near Fort Miller", 1822-1823 (Folder 27)
      Plate 9 [Koke 79]
    - "Glenns Falls", 1822 (Folder 28)
      Plate 6 [Koke 80]
    - "Rapids Above Hadley's Falls", 1822-1823 (Folder 28)
      Plate 4 [Koke 83]
    - "Palisades", 1823-1824 (Folder 28)
      Plate 19 [Koke 88] Two copies.
    - "New York, from Governor's Island", 1823-1824 (Folder 29)
      Plate 20 [Koke 89] Second state, uncolored. Third state.
    - "Hudson", 1825 (Folder 29)
      Plate 13 [Koke 91] Uncolored.
    - "Newburgh", 1825 (Folder 29)
      Plate 14 [Koke 93] Second state.
    - "West Point", 1825 (Folder 29)
      Plate 16 [Koke 94]
  - unspecified
    - "New York from Weehawk," after William Guy Wall(1792-after 1864), published by William G. Wall., 1823 (Folder 30)
      First state, colored. [Koke 95]
    - "New York from Heights near Brooklyn," after William Guy Wall (1792-after 1864)., 1823 (Folder 31)
      First state, published by William G. Wall. [Koke 96]
      Third state, published by G. & C. & H. Carvill, 1829.
    - "A Correct View of the Old Methodist Church in John Street N. York," after Joseph B. Smith and Peter C. Smith., 1823 (Folder 32)
      Colored [Koke 97]
    - "Fairmount Waterworks," after Thomas Doughty (1793-1856), 1823-1825 (Folder 33)
      Colored. [Koke 98]
      Two prints restruck in 1960.
    - "City Hall," after William Guy Wall (1792-after 1864), published by Behr & Kahl, New York, 1826. (Folder 34)
      Colored [Koke 110]
    - "The Monument to De Kalb," after Robert Mills (1751-1855), 1827 (Folder 35)
      Two copies, colored. [Koke 111]
  - Colored aquatints published in Fielding Lucas' Lucas' Progressive Drawing Book (Baltimore: Fielding Lucas, [1827-28]
    - "Falls of the Susquehanna Above Columbia", 1827 (Folder 36)
      Part II, plate 9 [Koke 122]
    - John Hazlehurst Boneval Latrobe (1803-1891), 1828 (Folder 36)
      Part II, plate 12 [Koke 125]
  - unspecified
    - "United States Military Academy, Looking South," after George Catlin (1796-1872), published by G. & C. & H. Carvill, 1829, 1828 (Folder 37)
      Second state, colored. [Koke 131]
    - "United States Military Academy, Looking North," after George Catlin (1796-1872), published by G. & C. & H. Carvill, 1829, 1828 (Folder 38)
      Second state, colored. [Koke 132]
    - "De Witt Clinton Memorial," after Charles P. Harrison., 1828 (Folder 39)
      Two copies [Koke 133]
    - "Niagara Falls. Part of the American Falls from the Foot of the Stair Case," after William James Bennett (1787-1844)., 1829 (Folder 40)
      [Koke 135]First state, published by H. I. Megarey, two copies, colored.
      Second state, published by Joseph Lord, ca. 1853.
    - "Niagara Falls. Part of the British Falls taken from Under the Table Rock," after William James Bennett (1787-1844)., 1829 (Folder 41)
      [Koke 136]First state, published by H. I. Megarey, two copies, colored.
    - "Junction of the Erie and Northern (Champlain) Canals," after John William Hill (1812-1879)., [1830-1832] (Folder 42)
      Colored proof in aquatint, lettered in pencil. [Koke 138]
    - "Unidentified Town and Canal Locks," after John William Hill (1812-1879)., [1830-1832] (Folder 43)
      Three stages of proof, all before letters. [Koke 139]
    - "Unidentified City, Possibly Troy," after John William Hill (1812-1879)., [1830-1832] (Folder 44)
      Proof before letters, etched in line. [Koke 140]
    - "Albany, N.Y.," after John William Hill (1812-1879)., [1832] (Folder 45)
      Proof before letters in aquatint. [Koke 141]
    - "Hudson River at Waterford, N.Y.," after John William Hill (1812-1879)., [1832] (Folder 46)
      Proof before letters in aquatint. [Koke 142]
    - "Matteawan, Manufacturing Village," after Orlando Neely, published by Orlando Neely, 1832. (Folder 47)
      Colored. [Koke 145]
    - "Capturing a Sperm Whale," after William Page (1811-1885), 1835 (Folder 48)
      Colored. [Koke 147]
    - "Broadway, New-York," after Thomas Hornor (1784-1844)., 1836 (Folder 49)
      Colored. [Koke 152]